This is Los Angeles, the second largest
city in the United States and the
cultural capital of the world. And this
was once the most extensive transit
system ever built. A network of street
cars, more than a,000 m long. 2,000
trains that ran daily, linking
neighborhoods across Southern
California.
>> The sad truth is we once had one of the
finest transit systems around. It was
called the Pacific Electric Railway.
Today, it's almost unimaginable. Good
quality, space efficient transit in a
city that's known for some of the worst
traffic on the planet.
>> Hardly a year goes by that somebody
doesn't come up with still another plan
to bring rapid transit to Southern
California. Yet, so far, all we've got
is buses that are no more rapid than
your average family car.
>> For years, street cars carried families
from their houses through orange groves
to the cities. Today, their descendants
do the same, but stuck in their cars for
hours. A century ago, street cars
transformed LA from nothing into
America's second largest city.
>> Relive the final years of the Los
Angeles street car system, fondly
remembered by older Angelinos as the
yellow cars. You'll return to the year
1956 to visit all of the remaining
street car lines in service and follow
them through to 1963 and their final
abandonment. But then they disappeared.
This is the story of one of the greatest
railway battles in American history.
It's a story about the man who built LA
street cars, and it's the story of why
they vanished.
1874, a judge named Robert Whitney built
the first public transit in LA, a single
horse car track. LA was a small farming
town, a handful of streets. But when the
railroads came, the population boomed.
Horse car lines sprang up around the
city. People wanted the market. But they
didn't just make their money by selling
tickets. They made money by selling
land. They divided tracks into parcels,
graded them, and supplied them with
water. Then they built transit. The lots
rose in value. People could commute to
consume or open businesses. These
neighborhoods were called street car
suburbs. Many cities where everything
could be reached within 15 minutes. one
of America's most traditional ways of
building. They built mixeduse buildings
as well as a variety of low and medium
density housing types. Apartments,
duplexes, forplexes, bungalow courts,
and single family homes. Many buildings
that are illegal to build today. Streets
were planned in a grid. The block
lengths were short and sidewalks were
fronted by multi-story businesses. They
built shaded arcades and ornamented
facades to give people something nice to
look at as they walked around. The ones
that survived intact are some of the
most desirable neighborhoods in the
entire United States.
Prudin Bodri came to California during
the gold rush. He started a business in
San Francisco selling shovels, but it
failed after fires burned all of it. So,
he moved to LA. He bought land like the
others and started developing. He owned
some hilly tracks near downtown, but it
was still too steep to access by horse
car. He wanted to make a profit on his
land. He needed a way to move people up
the slopes. Horse cars wouldn't work.
But Bodri had an answer from San
Francisco. Cable cars. At their peak,
they ran 17 hours a day with one coming
every 5 minutes. Most of the energy went
into the winding machinery and the
cables, which had to be replaced and
were heavy. They were superior to horse
cars, but they weren't reliable.
Luckily, in 1888, there was a
breakthrough miles away on the other
side of the country. Richmond, Virginia,
built America's first citywide electric
street car. A power plant generated
direct current sent through an overhead
wire. Each street car collected this
power with a roof mounted trolley pole
and sent it to onboard motors that
powered the axles. Then, current
returned through the rails to complete
the circuit. It spread like wildfire. By
1890, Charlie started replacing cable
cars across the country, and they were
coming to LA.
But they never got there because they
were too busy playing World of Warships.
World of Warships is free to play and
easy to jump into with friends. Hundreds
of historically inspired warships. From
destroyers and cruisers to battleships,
carriers, and submarines with updated
visuals and new content landing every
month. America just turned 250 and the
game is celebrating with a US
anniversary event running through July
15th. Each week unlocks narrative
stages, historical paintings, and
rewards along the path to American
independence. Play a single battle and
you get a free anniversary bundle on
top. Click the first link in the
description and use code USA250.
Whether you're new or returning, you'll
get a million credits, a week of
premium, and two premium American ships,
the cruiser Albany, and the destroyer
Smith. It's also on console as World of
Warships, Legends.
Moses Hazeline Sherman saw the potential
of the new electric trolleys. He'd
earned a fortune in Arizona, but he was
convinced LA was the real jackpot. In
1890, he started a company that built
multiple street car lines across LA.
When his competitors went bankrupt, he
bought them up. He consolidated 35 mi of
electric lines, 21 mi of cable lines,
and 14 mi of horsear lines. This became
the yellow car system. Moses would own
the largest street car railway operation
in LA, but he got too greedy. And there
was another man who saw lane track as a
way to fortune, and he was coming for
the yellow cars. Henry Huntington was no
small man. His uncle was one of the big
four that built the transcontinental
railroad. After his uncle died, Henry
expected to take control of his vast
railroad empire, but he was betrayed. A
group of Southern Pacific shareholders
blocked Henry from ascending to the
presidency. Uncompromising, he sold his
shares for $50 million. The buyer was a
man named Eh Haramman. Heramman was one
of the guilded age Robert Barons, known
as the little giant of Wall Street. He
was actually a kind of small man, but
big in the rail business. Henry was
furious at the South Pacific, so he took
his millions to Los Angeles. If he
couldn't have his uncle Southern Pacific
Empire, he would have to build his own.
When Sherman was late on his bond
payments, Henry used the opportunity to
buy the entire yellow car system. And he
wasn't done. By 1902, his company
started building its own lines. Pacific
Electric's first new line ran to Long
Beach. The red cars were electric. They
were newer, faster, cleaner, and more
frequent than Southern Pacific trains.
But they also had an owner driven more
by spite than capital. Henry Huntington
didn't care about profits. Every extra
cent earned was invested back into
building new lines. Huntington wanted
revenge for being kicked out of Southern
Pacific, and he was going to try and
take them out of business. But they saw
that he was coming, and Heramman wasn't
going to go easily. Henry built his
tracks next to Southern Pacific routes.
With his faster standard gauge trains,
he could compete with Southern Pacific's
freight shipping and steal their
passengers. But Southern Pacific wasn't
blind.
In 1903, Haramman made a move to level
the playing field. He purchased an
entire rail company called the Hook
Line, big enough to directly compete in
LA. Herman had deeper pockets, but
Huntington didn't care. When a rail
franchise went up for auction, both of
them went for it. The bids kept going
higher and higher. A franchise worth
$5,000 doubled in value, then tripled,
then tripled again, and sold to
Haramman. Huntington was defeated. He
couldn't compete against Haramman's
wallet. In a peace deal, Haramman was
given a joint stake in Pacific Electric.
Huntington was forced to accept his
rival as a business partner with Veto
Power on the company board.
But he and Heramman clashed constantly
with competing priorities. Huntington
wanted to run passenger lines to his
empty, undeveloped lots. For him, the
rail line was a loss leader. He was
willing to take on debt as long as his
land went up in value. But Haramman was
the head of a transcontinental shipping
empire. He wanted the Pacific Electric
to profit on freight shipping and
reliable ticket sales and established
towns. Haramman could veto anything that
went against his interest. Huntington
wanted to build a line to San Diego
County for a new development, but Herman
vetoed it because it competed with his
own plans. Frustrated, Huntington
established a new railroad company, the
Los Angeles Inter urban with full
ownership and built new routes from Los
Angeles to Orange County. The business
arrangement wasn't working. Southern
Pacific and Huntington agreed to another
deal. Huntington got a cash payout and
the yellow car that let him focus on
real estate. and Southern Pacific got
the Red Car, the largest ledger transit
system in the world. It linked more than
50 communities across four counties, Los
Angeles, Riverside, San Bernardino, and
Orange. At its peak in 1924, 2,000 daily
trains ran on 1,100 m of track, more
track mileage than Germany's highspeed
rail system today, more than the
combined lengths of all Shinkansen lines
north of Tokyo, and even more route
length than the modern New York City
subway, London Underground, and Paris
Metro systems combined. But then they
disappeared.
It's the 1980s. An investigative
journalist named Jonathan Quinty finds
something in a Chicago warehouse. Two
battered cartons covered in dust. Inside
are transcripts, testimonials, and
filings from a forgotten 1949 court
case. United States v National City
Lines. He discovers something. In 1933,
a man from General Motors approached a
man named Leroy Fitzgerald, a 7th grade
dropout who was operating a small
Minnesota bus service with his brothers.
Young, ambitious, and small enough to be
controlled, the man offered Fitzgerald a
deal that was too good to pass up.
>> We'll invest in your company. We'll
finance your acquisitions, help you with
technical surveys and negotiations.
We'll give you financial backing,
anything you need. But we do need one
thing in return. With our money, you're
going to buy street car companies in
small cities, and you'll replace all of
them with our buses.
>> Fitzgerald couldn't believe his ears. He
was going to be a very wealthy man. All
he had to do was go along with General
Motors his scheme. They helped him
establish a holding company called
National City Lines. Then with GM
funding, Fitzgerald bought out and
dismantled electric street car networks
in city after city. He started small,
Illinois, Gillsburg, East St. Louis, and
Juliet. As his business growth started
to appear more legitimate, he moved on
to Oklahoma, Alabama, Texas, and Iowa.
He and General Motors took over but
Montana then Lincoln Nebraska. The
scheme worked so well that other
corporations piled in to invest.
Firestone Tire and Rubber, Philips
Petroleum, and strangely Mac Trucks,
General Motors direct competitor.
Fitzgerald took over Salt Lake City,
Portland, Tampa, and Mobile. They ripped
out the street cars and signed contracts
to buy buses built by General Motors
with Firestone tires that ran on
standard oil diesel. One by one,
Baltimore, El Paso, and Spokane all fell
to Fitzgerald and General Motors. Then
they set their sights on the biggest
transit system of all, Los Angeles.
In 1947, the Justice Department caught
on. They filed an antitrust lawsuit. The
conspirators were found guilty of one
charge to monopolize the sale of buses
and supplies. Their contracts with
transit companies to exclusively buy
their products was ruled illegal, but
the defendants were acquitted of the
charge to monopolize transportation
itself. The penalty was a slap on the
wrist. The oil and auto companies were
each fined $5,000. Individual company
officials were fined $1 each. But when
Quinty reviewed the case files, it
didn't make sense. If they were just
building buses, why would General Motors
go into business with its direct
competitor, Mac Trucks? Their goal
wasn't just to profit on bus fairs and
bus supplies alone. The only way to make
it make sense is if bus revenue was
secondary to the sale of automobiles
after the street cars were killed. After
the tracks were paved over, General
Motors profited by selling cars. Mack by
selling trucks. The economics are
obvious. One bus can eliminate 35
automobiles. One street car, subway, or
rail transit vehicle can supplant 50
passenger cars. One train can displace
1,000 cars or a fleet of 150 cargo laden
trucks. A coordinated scheme to
systematically accelerate carcentric
development and replace trains and
transit with traffic. But the street car
companies were already having problems
before General Motors came. By the
1920s, the Los Angeles basin was
producing 20% of the global supply of
oil. Cheap local fuel caused more cars
to appear on LA roads. They became a
symbol of the American dream. As
industry boomed, more people flocked to
the city. Demand for land rose.
Speculators assumed that holding and
subdividing land would generate return
on investment as land values continued
to rise.
Speculative real estate finance helped
set the stage for the Great Depression.
Before, banks expected a 50% down
payment for a home with a balloon
payment for the rest of the loan due at
the end of a 5-year term. But in the
Great Depression, banks were desperate
for cash. They wouldn't allow people to
extend the balloon payment. When they
couldn't pay, the banks seized the
homes. Shanty towns appeared across the
country. Congress passed the National
Housing Act and created the Federal
Housing Administration. They'd ensure
banks when homeowners couldn't pay. It
actively promoted home ownership by
guaranteeing a federal backing for home
loans with long payback periods. To
reduce their risk on these longer
mortgages, the FHA used color-coded maps
made by the Homeowners Loan Corporation.
They pushed loans away from areas
flagged as hazardous for investment and
wealthier all-white homogeneous suburban
areas were seen as safe. In order for
people to qualify for loans with federal
backing, urban planners and developers
mandated strict zoning, uniform housing
types, and requirements for lot sizes
and setbacks. They put restrictions on
subdividing lots or building new
dwellings and required approval by
committee for any new building designs.
They actively steered for cookie cutter
single family suburbs that were designed
for cars, not dense transit. While
Huntington risked his own capital to go
in direct competition with Southern
Pacific and bring down prices, the state
directly funded freeways that were built
alongside the railway corridors.
As cars became more affordable, the
problem for street cars spiraled. As
they increased on the same roads, street
cars had to compete for space. They got
stuck in traffic and they weren't able
to make their schedules, sometimes
running 30 minutes late. They used to go
40 or 50 mph, but now slowed down into
the 10s. Then there was falling
ridership, which meant declining
revenue. Declining revenue and the
quality of service got even worse. In
1944, they reached a breaking point. The
yellow car was sold to Fitzgerald, who
followed the GM playbook to rip out the
lines and replace them with buses. In
1947, Pacific Electric made one last
ditch effort, asking the city and state
for a ride ofway in the center of the
under construction Hollywood Freeway.
With a fully owned road, their cars
wouldn't get stuck in traffic, and they
wouldn't be able to transport twice as
many people per hour as eight lanes of
cars. For those who valued speed and no
congestion, this was an obvious bargain.
But the proposal was rejected because it
interfered with freeway construction.
The urban planners started to look at
the redline areas as urban blight that
needed to be demolished. The bunker hill
tracks developed by prudent bodri were
once wealthy, but the mansions were
subdivided. They house low-income
residents and businesses that sprang
from the community. They gave the poor
access to valuable land and commerce
through small units. But it was marked
as high risk on the redlinining map. In
1949, it was bulldozed to build the
stack, the world's first four-level
stack interchange, connecting the new
Hollywood Freeway with the Royo Seiko.
The rest of Bunker Hill was bulldozed in
the 50s and60s as part of more slum
clearance policies. Just to the north,
the government forcibly evicted 1,800
families from the Chavez Ravine to build
Dodger Stadium for a baseball team that
used to be called the Charlie Dodgers.
One by one, the street car lines were
closed and the tracks were ripped out.
The last red car on the Long Beach line,
the first line built by Pacific
Electric, made its final trip in 1961.
Almost immediately, the city realized
its mistakes. They tried to raise $500
million to rebuild a rail system. But by
the time of the oil crisis, the cost of
constructing 116 mi of track, less than
1/6 the size of the red car, rose from
500 million to more than $6.6 billion.
The tradition of storefronts attached to
the sidewalks was over. Businesses and
houses were required to have parking
lots in front of detached buildings. By
the 1970s, more than half of Los Angeles
was zoned exclusively for single family
homes.
What was once a dream is fast becoming a
reality.
The long- aaited metro rail is on track
and headed for Los Angeles.
>> In 1980, the city passed Proposition A,
a half cent sales tax to fund a new
metro.
When it arrives not long from now, Metro
Rail will prove to be the vital link to
providing a muchneeded balanced
transportation system for the area. A
total system that complements our
comprehensive network of buses and
freeways and one that will foster the
growth, vitality, and economic
development of this international
metropolis, Los Angeles. A decade later,
a new light rail opened. The blue A-ine
followed the original red car route to
Long Beach. In 1993, the red beline
opened, LA's first modern subway. For
the past three decades, LA has been on a
transit building spree. And now, Los
Angeles is constructing more new rail
than any other city in the United
States.
The 28x28 initiative is trying to
complete 28 infrastructure projects in
time for the next summer Olympic Games.
A two-mile regional connector has
already been added downtown. A new
transit hub was built at the airport and
a new 9mm extension of the Purple D line
is currently under construction.
Ironically, after 100 years, LA is
returning to a traditional way of
building. Senate Bill 79 overrides the
zoning laws and parking minimums that
made it illegal to rebuild density along
the transit corridor. Thousands of new
homes are planned in a city with a
severe housing deficit. Los Angeles has
a long way to go, but maybe one day it
could once again have the greatest
transit system in the world.